So there are a few things
هناك بعض الأشياء
that bring us humans together in the way that an election does.
التي تجمعنا سوياً كبشر في الطريقة التي ننتخب بها.
We stand in elections; we vote in elections;
نحن نصطف في الإنتخابات، ونقوم بالتصويت،
we observe elections.
ونراقب الإنتخابات
Our democracies rely on elections.
تعتمد ديموقراطياتنا على الإنتخابات.
We all understand why we have elections,
وجميعنا يفهم لماذا نقيم الإنتخابات،
and we all leave the house on the same day
وجميعنا يغادر المنزل في نفس اليوم
to go and vote.
ويذهب للتصويت.
We cherish the opportunity to have our say,
نحن نستثمر الفرصة لنقول كلمتنا،
to help decide the future of the country.
لنساعد في تقرير مستقبل بلادنا.
The fundamental idea is that politicians
الفكرة الأساسية هي أن السياسيون
are given mandate to speak for us,
يتم إعطاؤهم تفويض للحديث نيابة عنا،
to make decisions on our behalf
لأخذ القرارات نيابة عنا
that affect us all.
التي تؤثر علينا جميعاً.
Without that mandate, they would be corrupt.
بدون ذلك التفويض، قد يصبحوا فاسدين.
Well unfortunately, power corrupts,
بكل أسف، السلطة تُفسد،
and so people will do lots of things
ولذا سيفعل الناس الكثير من الأشياء
to get power and to stay in power,
للوصول والبقاء في السلطة،
including doing bad things to elections.
وضمن هذه الأشياء فعل أشياء سيئة في الإنتخابات.
You see, even if the idea
كما ترون، حتى لو كانت فكرة
of the election is perfect,
الإنتخابات مثالية،
running a countrywide election is a big project,
فإن إجراء الإنتخابات على مستوى البلاد تظل مشروعاً ضخماً،
and big projects are messy.
والمشروع الضخم قد تتخلله الفوضى.
Whenever there is an election,
كلما كانت هناك إنتخابات،
it seems like something always goes wrong,
يبدو كأن هناك شيئاً يمضي بصورة خاطئة،
someone tries to cheat,
أحدهم يحاول الغش،
or something goes accidentally awry --
أو يخفق شئ بصورة مقصودة--
a ballot box goes missing here,
يختفي صندوق إقتراع هنا،
chads are left hanging over here.
تُنسى بعض أوراق الإقتراع هنا.
To make sure as few things as possible go wrong,
وللتأكد من تقل نسبة الخطأ،
we have all these procedures around the election.
فان لدينا كل هذه الإجراءات حول الإنتخابات.
So for example, you come to the polling station,
على سبيل المثال، أنت تأتي لمركز الإقتراع،
and a poll station worker asks for your ID
ويسألك عامل المركز من إثبات هويتك
before giving you a ballot form
قبل أن يعطيك ورقة التصويت
and asking you to go into a voting booth
ويطلب منك التوجّه لصندوق الإقتراع
to fill out your vote.
لتدلي بصوتك.
When you come back out, you get to drop your vote
حينما تعود أدراجك، تكون قد رميت بصوتك
into the ballot box
داخل صندوق الإقتراع
where it mixes with all the other votes,
حيث تختلط جميع الأصوات،
so that no one knows how you voted.
بحيث لا يعلم شخص ما لمن أدليت بصوتك.
Well, what I want us to think about for a moment
حسناً، ما أريد التفكير به لوهلة
is what happens after that,
هو ما يحدث عقب ذلك،
after you drop your vote into the ballot box.
بعد أن ترمي بصوتك داخل صندوق الإقتراع.
And most people would go home
وسيذهب معظم الناس لمنازلهم
and feel sure that their vote has been counted,
متأكدين بأن أصواتهم قد تم حسبها،
because they trust
لأنهم يثقون
that the election system works.
في نظام الإنتخابات.
They trust that election workers and election observers
ويثقون بأن لجنة الإنتخابات ومراقبيها
do their jobs and do their jobs correctly.
يؤدون واجباتهم بصورة صحيحة.
The ballot boxes go to counting places.
تذهب صناديق الإقتراع لمراكز الفرز.
They're unsealed and the votes are poured out
يتم تفريغها وتصنيفها
and laboriously counted.
ثم عدّ الأصوات.
Most of us have to trust
يتوجب علينا الثقة
that that happens correctly for our own vote,
بأن ذلك سيحدث بصورة صحيحة لأصواتنا،
and we all have to trust that that happens correctly
يتوجب علينا جميعاً الثقة بأن ذلك يمضي بصورة صحيحة
for all the votes in the election.
لكل المصوّتين في الإنتخابات.
So we have to trust a lot of people.
لذا ينبغي أن نثق في الكثير من الناس.
We have to trust a lot of procedures.
ينبغي أن نثق بالكثير من الإجراءات.
And sometimes we even have to trust computers.
وبعض الأحيان ينبغي أن نثق بالحواسيب.
So imagine hundreds of millions of voters
إذاً تخيلوا مئات الملايين من الناخبين
casting hundreds of millions of votes,
يدلون بمئات الملايين من الأصوات،
all to be counted correctly
ويتم حسبها جميعاً بصورة صحيحة
and all the things that can possibly go wrong
ويحتمل أن تمضي كل الأشياء بصورة خاطئة
causing all these bad headlines,
مسببة عنواين رئيسية سيئة للصحف.
and you cannot help but feel exhausted at the idea
ولا تستطيع فعل شئ سوى أن تشعر بالملل من ...
of trying to make elections better.
فكرة تحسين الأداء الإنتخابي.
Well in the face of all these bad headlines,
حسناً في ظل هذه العناوين الرئيسية السيئة،
researchers have taken a step back
قام الباحثون بأخذ خطوات
and thought about how we can do elections differently.
وفكروا حول ما يستطيعون فعله بصورة مختلفة للإنتخابات.
They've zoomed out and looked at the big picture.
لقد قاموا بالتركيز على الصورة الأكبر.
And the big picture is this:
والصورة الأكبر هي هذا:
elections should be verifiable.
ينبغي أن تكون الإنتخابات قابلة للتحقق منها.
Voters should be able to check
ينبغي أن يقدر الناخبون على التأكد
that their votes are counted correctly,
من أن أصواتهم محسوبة بصورة صحيحة،
without breaking election secrecy,
بدون إفشاء أسرار العملية الإنتخابية،
which is so very important.
التي هي غاية في الأهمية.
And that's the tough part.
وذلك هو الجزء الأصعب.
How do we make an election system completely verifiable
كيف يمكننا جعل نظام الإنتخابات قابل للتحقق منه كليا،
while keeping the votes
بينما نبقي على سرية الأصوات
absolutely secret?
بصورة قاطعة؟
Well, the way we've come up with
حسناً، الحل الذي توصلناه له
uses computers
باستخدام الحواسيب،
but doesn't depend on them.
لكن دون الإعتماد عليها.
And the secret is the ballot form.
ويكمن السرّ في ورقة الإقتراع.
And if you look closely at these ballot forms,
وإذا أمعنتم النظر في ورقة الإقتراع،
you'll notice that the candidate list
ستلاحظون أن قائمة المرشحين
is in a different order on each one.
مختلفة في الترتيب لكل شخص.
And that means, if you mark your choices on one of them
وذلك يعني، أنك إذا أخترت أحدهم
and then remove the candidate list,
ثم تزيل قائمة المرشحين،
I won't be able to tell from the bit remaining
فلن أقدر أنا من معرفة ..
what your vote is for.
لمن أدليت بصوتك.
And on each ballot form there is this encrypted value
وفي كل ورقة إقتراع هناك قيّم مشفرة
in the form of this 2D barcode
في شكل شريط مرمّز ثنائي الأبعاد
on the right.
على اليمين.
And there's some complicated cryptography
وهناك تشفير غاية في التعقيد
going on in there,
يجري هناك،
but what's not complicated
لكن الشئ السهل
is voting with one of these forms.
هو التصويت عبر أحد هذه الأوراق.
So we can let computers do all the complicated cryptography for us,
إذاً يمكن الإعتماد على الحواسيب في التشفير المعقد
and then we'll use the paper for verification.
ثم نستخدم الأوراق للتحقق من صحة ذلك.
So this is how you vote.
إذاً هكذا تقوم بالتصويت
You get one of these ballot forms at random,
أنت تحصل على أحد أوراق الإقتراع هذه بصورة عشوائية،
and then you go into the voting booth,
ثم تذهب بها لصندوق الإقتراع،
and you mark your choices,
وتدلي بصوتك عبر الإشارة،
and you tear along a perforation.
وتقطع ذلك الجزء.
And you shred the candidate list.
وتمّزق قائمة المرشحين.
And the bit that remains, the one with your marks --
والجزء المتبقي، الذي عليه صوتك،
this is your encrypted vote.
هاهو الصوت المشفّر.
So you let a poll station worker
وتجعل موظفي مركز التصويت
scan your encrypted vote.
يمسحون الصوت المشفّر ضوئياً.
And because it's encrypted,
ولأنه مشفّر،
it can be submitted, stored
يمكن إدخاله، وتخزينه
and counted centrally
وحسابه مركزياً
and displayed on a website
ويتم عرضه على الموقع الإلكتروني
for anyone to see, including you.
ليراه الجميع، وضمنهم أنت.
So you take this encrypted vote
لذا يمكنك أخذ الصوت المشفّر
home as your receipt.
معك إلى البيت مثل الفاتورة.
And after the close of the election,
وبعد نهاية الإنتخابات،
you can check that your vote was counted
يمكنك التأكد من عدّ صوتك
by comparing your receipt
بمقارنة الفاتورة التي لديك
to the vote on the website.
مع الأصوات على الموقع الإلكتروني.
And remember, the vote is encrypted
تذكروا، أن الصوت مشفّر
from the moment you leave the voting booth,
من اللحظة التي غادرت فيها صندوق الإقتراع،
so if an election official wants to find out how you voted,
ولذا، إن أراد موظف المركز الإنتخابي معرفة تصويتك
they will not be able to.
فانه لن يقدر على ذلك.
If the government wants to find out how you voted,
وإذا أرادت الحكومة معرفة ذلك،
they won't be able to.
فلن تقدر على ذلك.
No hacker can break in
لا يستطيع قرصان إختراق النظام
and find out how you voted.
ومعرفة لمن أدليت بصوتك.
No hacker can break in and change your vote,
لا يستطيع قرصان إختراق النظام وتغيير صوتك،
because then it won't match your receipt.
لأنه لن يتطابق مع فاتورتك حينئذ.
Votes can't go missing
لن تضيع أصوات،
because then you won't find yours when you look for it.
لأنك لن تجد صوتك عندما تتأكد منه (عبر الموقع).
But the election magic doesn't stop there.
لكن سحر الإنتخابات لا يتوقف هناك.
Instead, we want to make the whole process
عوضاً عن ذلك نريد أن نجعل العملية برمتها
so transparent
غايةً في الشفافية
that news media and international observers
بحيث تستطيع وسائل الإعلام والمراقبون الدوليون
and anyone who wants to
وأي شخص يريد
can download all the election data
تحميل كل بيانات الإنتخابات
and do the count themselves.
ويقوموا بعدّها بأنفسهم.
They can check that all the votes were counted correctly.
يمكنهم التأكد من أن جميع الأصوات تم عدّها بصورة صحيحة.
They can check
يمكنهم التأكد من أن
that the announced result of the election
النتائج المعلنة للإنتخابات
is the correct one.
هي نتائج صحيحة.
And these are elections
وأن هذه إنتخابات
by the people, for the people.
من الناس، ولأجل الناس،
So the next step for our democracies
إذاً فالخطوة القادمة لديموقراطياتنا
are transparent
هي إنتخابات شفافة
and verifiable elections.
وقابلة للتحقق منها.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)